KRISTINA ULICNA

PhD Candidate (final year) @ University College London

London, United Kingdom

+44(0)7754385111 (UK)

linkedin.com/in/KristinaUlicna

twitter.com/KristinaUlicna

github.com/KristinaUlicna

Computational Skills

Strongest programming language: Python

Experience with *supervised* (segmentation & classification), weakly supervised (multiple-instance), self-supervised (variational autoencoders) & unsupervised (timesequence trajectory clustering) learning & dimensionality reduction app (PCA, UMAP)

- Machine learning libraries: skimage, sklearn, torch, pytorch lightning, tensorflow 2.0, keras, innereye-deeplearning, btrack, HPACellSegmentator, CSBDeep
- Standard & scientific libraries: jupyter numpy, scipy, pandas, json, os, matplotlib, pyplot, h5py, tqdm, napari

Work comfortably with GitHub (git), iPython (jupyter) notebooks, LaTeX (overleaf) & Sigmaplot Statistics software

Analysis of **DNA sequencing** data:

- SnapGene software: vector construction
- CLC workbench: Sanger sequencing
- Nanopore sequencing platform interface

Laboratory Skills

Molecular biology & vector construction:

- PCR (RT-, colony-, sequential-, nested-)
- Plasmid preparation (mini- & midi-prep)
- Restriction endonuclease gene cloning
- · Gateway cloning & Gibson Assembly
- Preparation & purification of mRNA
- Cell-free protein synthesis (PURExpress)

Cell engineering & tissue culture:

- Stable cell transfection via lipofection or lentiviral & retroviral transduction
- · Colony selection with antibiotic titration
- Tet(Dox)-inducible gene expression
- · Cell fractionation & organelle isolation Induction of cell differentiation (DMSO)
- Cell culture (passaging) with cell lines: MDCK, HeLa, HL60, CHO, HEK-293, MCF-7/ 10A, MDA-MB-231, HMLER, LNCaP, HaCaT

Cell-based assays & imaging platforms:

 IncuCyte ZOOM live-cell analysis system cell proliferation assay with colorimetric cell viability, ratiometric [Ca2+] release & fluorimetric protein release assays

Gene expression detection methods:

- SDS-PAGE, Western (dot) blotting
- Immunocytochemistry (IF cell staining)
- Extra- & intracellular flow cytometry
- FACS-sorted clonal cell line expansion

Summary

As a PhD researcher at UCL, I apply my programming & laboratory skills in a multi-disciplinary project combining cell biology, computational single-cell tracking & deep learning. I focus on Python software development for large data analysis to identify biological patterns influencing cancer cell cycling control mechanisms. I am a practical, detail-oriented wet-lab scientist with cell engineering background, experienced in dry-lab machine learning research applied to single-cell biology. I have demonstrated my leadership skills in individual & collective settings, which I gained through UK & US work experience in academic biomedical research groups & international bio-/medical & microscopy imaging research teams in leading technological companies, and through my involvement in volunteering & community projects.

Education

Oct 2018 -Nov 2022 (expected)

PhD in Biosciences, BBSRC LIDo DTP Programme, UCL | London, UK

- · Provisional Thesis Title: "Deep Lineage with Deep Learning: Tracking Single-Cell Heterogeneity within Non-/Cancer Cell Lines", advised by G. Charras & A. R. Lowe
- Fully funded via London Interdisciplinary Doctoral Training Partnership (LIDo DTP)
- Yale Stem Cell Center. Yale School of Medicine exchange visitor: postponed to '22
- Merit-based Scholarships: Talents of the New Europe '19, Students to the World '19

Sep 2014 -Jul 2018

BSc Biomedical Science (Hons), King's College London | London, UK

- First Class Hons (76%) Biomedical Science with Extramural Year in Pharmacology
- Awards & Scholarships: Desmond Tutu Scholarship '14, Best Lay Article Award '15

Research Experience

Mar 2019 -Present

PhD Researcher, the "DeepTree" project @ UCL | London, UK

- · Co-developed a robust, supervision-free, deep learning-based tracking pipeline for deep lineage analysis of large time-lapse microscopy data in non-/cancer cell lines
- · Published two computational framework manuscripts (U-Net, CNN, btrack multiobject tracking algorithm) with applicability to single cell cycle duration predictions
- Trained VAE representations of single-cell time-sequence image glimpse datasets
- Analysed multigenerational lineage trees (>20,000 single cells) to identify heritable proliferation characteristics which predispose cells to commit to fast divider fates
- Supervised Masters Thesis project to develop an Al-based cell segmentation tool

Apr 2021 -Sep 2021

- Research Intern @ Microsoft Research Cambridge | Cambridge, UK
- Developed an Al-based end-to-end pipeline to classify subcellular protein localisation in single cells from Human Protein Atlas' dataset of weakly labelled confocal microscopy images using Azure computing & InnerEye Deep Learning OS toolkit
- Trained a competitively-performing model (MIL / SimCLR & BYOL architectures) upon evaluation with Kaggle competition authors (Prof. Emma Lundberg's Lab)
- Summarised project to Health Intelligence Lab leadership at End-of-Internship talk

Sep 2016 -Aug 2017

Industrial Trainee @ Crescendo Biologics Ltd. | Cambridge, UK

- Engineered novel, universal tool cell line for early drug discovery, i.e. phage display selection & functional screening of antibody fragment oncology therapeutics
- · Presented project outcomes to senior scientists & company management board

Jun 2016 -Sep 2016

Cancer Research UK Intern @ Cambridge University | Cambridge, UK

· S. Bohndiek Lab: Characterised anti-angiogenic drug effects via breast cancer cell-based growth, viability assays to evaluate oxygen role in cancer progression

Jun 2015 -Aug 2015

Visiting Scholar, Whitehead Institute @ MIT | Cambridge, USA · R. Weinberg's Lab: Investigated determinants of cancer cell invasion, metastasis

& tumour stroma immunomodulation upon epithelial-to-mesenchymal transition

Teaching Experience

May 2021

"Smart Microscopy" Workshop @ ZEISS

| Gothenburg, Sweden • Trained 30+ intermediate-level attendees at "Train Your Own Model" hands-on

workshop session to use (bio)image analysis tools (napari, jupyter notebooks) to annotate cell imaging data to train deep learning model to classify cell cycle state

Jan 2021 -Dec 2021

Google Certified Trainer for AI Tech & Tools | Bratislava, Slovakia • Empowering non-tech professionals by leveraging their expertise & leadership in

Mar 2020 -

Al tech field via Al-basics talks & workshops with Google Slovakia outreach team Graduate Teaching Assistant @ UCL BIOC0016 module | London, UK

Present

• Co-designed an iPython-based practical session for 70+ undergraduate students for introductory concepts in bioimage analysis, bioinformatics & machine learning to hand-label image mini-dataset & train simplified classifier of cell mitotic state

Jun 2020

"Introduction to Deep Learning" @ UCL Cancer Domain | London, UK

- Delivered beginner-friendly masterclass series for 100+ interdisciplinary scientists with real-life examples of deep learning-based bioimage analysis from PhD project
- Demonstrated deep learning benefits, contrasted deep learning to computer vision methods, emphasised fundamentals of 'learning' component & current challenges

Language Skills

native proficiency Czech bilingual proficiency

full professional proficiency **English**

IELTS & iBT TOEFL language test certificates

limited working proficiency

High-school certificate; German evening classes

Awards & Scholarships

- 2021 **30 under 30** @ Forbes Slovakia
- 2019 European Union Council Delegate
- 2017 **United Nations** Assembly Delegate
- 2017 GSK Healthcare STEM Awardee

Hobbies & Interests

- Ballroom dancing; standard & Latin style (UK national partner competitions level)
- Bachata & salsa social dancing (int/adv)
- Long-distance running (half-marathons)
- Playing tennis (competitively at school)

General -

- Member of the University of London DanceSport Society (active competitor)
- Member of London Stem Cell Network
- Member of British Pharmacol Society
- EU / Slovak driving licence | B type
- · First aid training course certificate

Academic Referees

Prof Guillaume Charras

- PhD project advisor; Professor in Cell & Tissue Biophysics @ London Centre for Nanotechnology & Dept. of Cell & Developmental Biology @ UCL
- Web. https://charraslab.com/
- g.charras@ucl.ac.uk Fmail⁻

Dr Alan R. Lowe

- PhD project advisor; Al for Science Fellow @ The Alan Turing Institute & Associate Professor of Biophysics at Inst. of Struct. & Molec. Biology @ UCL
- http://lowe.cs.ucl.ac.uk/ Weh
- a.lowe@ucl.ac.uk Email:

Prof Geraint Thomas

- LIDo PhD Programme Deputy Director; Professor of Biochemistry at Dept. of Cell & Developmental Biology @ UCL
- Web: https://www.lido-dtp.ac.uk/ g.thomas@ucl.ac.uk Email:

Leadership & Teamwork Experience

Student Ambassador, LIDo PhD Programme @ UCL Sep 2019 -| London, UK Present • Outlined programme structure & shared own experience with new student cohorts • Guided individual students through responsibilities with changing rotation projects

| Bratislava, Slovakia 2015 -Jury Member, LEAF Award @ LEAF

2017 Shortlisted self-driven, talented students with community involvement in jury team

University Mentor, Talent Guide @ LEAF 2016 -| Bratislava, Slovakia 2018 · Counselled college choices with gifted high-schoolers & edited personal statements

Specialist Trainings & Summer Schools

Institut Curie & Sorbonne Université Apr - May | Paris, France 2022

• 'International course of Cell Biology & Cancer' with the 'Science & Life' workshop

Nov - Dec Jumping Rivers Ltd. I London, UK 2020 • Two intermediate courses: 'Machine Learning with Python', 'Python & Tensorflow'

University of Hong Kong | Hong Kong, China

Practical course 'Advanced Imaging: Deep Learning in Live Imaging & Cell Biology'

University of Genova | Genova. Italy

· 'Machine Learning Crash Course' covering theoretical foundations & core concepts University of Cambridge | Cambridge, UK

Sep - Oct • Two beginners courses: 'Solving Biological Problems', 'Statistical Analysis' using R

> **Johns Hopkins University** | Baltimore, USA

> • Interactive class 'The History of Disease' by Centre for Talented Youth (CTY JHU)

Science Popularisation Activities

Universal Expo Milano 2015 Sep 2015 | Milan, Italy

• Presented ongoing research as national team member to expert & lay audience

May 2014 Intel International Science & Engineering Fair | Los Angeles, USA

• Shortlisted finalist at world's largest pre-college science competition (poster talk)

International Congress of Young Investigators | Zaragoza, Spain

· Invited as 'Absolute Winner at the Festival of Science & Technology' & recipient of 'The Special Award by the Dean of the Faculty of Natural Sciences'

Invited Talks

Jul 2013

Aug - Sep

Jun - Jul

Jun - Jul

2019

2019

2016

2012

2022 Speaker | Al for Image Analysis @ Analytica 2022 Conference Fair | Munich, Germany

Speaker | Machine Learning Methods Advances @ Recursion CytoData Society Meeting Al Microscopy Symposium @ The Allen Institute for Brain Science & AlVIA Speaker | "See the Hidden": Future of Al in Microscopy Workshop @ Leica Microsystems Panelist I

Panelist | "Women in AI for Global Health" Session @ Mozilla Festival Tech Conference

UCL Biolmage Analysis Interest Group @ Laboratory of Molecular Cell Biology 2020 Speaker I Imperial College Brain Sciences Seminar @ UK Dementia Research Institute Speaker | Python Software Foundation Pro Network Meetup @ #PyLadies Dublin

Contributed Talks

2021 Poster Women in Machine Learning (WiML) Workshop @ NeurIPS Conference Crick Biolmage Analysis Symposium (CBIAS) @ The Francis Crick Institute Poster

Women in Data Science (WiDS) Worldwide Conference @ Stanford University Poster

Speaker I Virtual Seminars in Biomedical Science @ Imperial College London

2020 Poster London Stem Cell Network Annual Symposium @ The Francis Crick Institute Society of Biomolecular Imaging & Informatics High Content Conference Poster Speaker |. UCL Institute of Structural & Molecular Biology Postgraduate Symposium

2019 Speaker | UCL Institute of Structural & Molecular Biology Friday Wrap @ Birkbeck Speaker | Quantitative Systems Biology Workshop @ King's College London

Poster | UCL Graduate Student Symposium @ Francis Crick Institute

Publications

Ulicna, K., Vallardi, G., Charras, G. & Lowe, A.R. (2021). Automated deep lineage tree analysis using a Bayesian single cell tracking approach. Frontiers in Computer Science, Computer Vision: Methods & Tools for Bioimage Analysis | Frontiers | BioRxiv | GitHub repository

Ulicna, K., Ho, L.T.L., Soelistyo, C.J., Day, N.J. & Lowe, A.R. (2022). Convolutional neural networks for classifying chromatin morphology in live cell imaging. Methods in Molecular Biology, Springer Nature Protocols (accepted; in press) | GitHub repository